A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Penitentiary, 1796-1991 (bulk 1906-1970)
Library of Virginia
- Series II. Prisoner Records, 1865-1990., Extent: 79.22 cubic feet of records, 128 volumes and 16 reels of microfilm. (Box 9-384, 694-696., Volume 1-127, 270., Microfilm Misc. Reels 5989-6004.)
  - Series II. Subseries A. Registers, 1865-1990. (Box 9-18., Volumes 1-127., Microfilm Misc. Reels 5989-6004.)
    - Series II.A.I. Prisoner Registers, 1865-1980. (Volumes 1-49.)
      - II.A.I.1 Prisoner Registers and Indexes 1865-1942. (Volumes 1-34.)
        Prisoner Register No. 10 includes prisoners admitted from 4 November 1912 to 15 April 1916 (inmate number 11083 to 14033). The register includes date received, name of prisoner, race, where sentenced, crime, term, birthplace (city or county and state), age, term expired, days lost, discharged, location and remarks. A separate volume indexes this register. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [Register, Misc. Reel 5993, frame 0001-0257; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0328-0363]
        Prisoner Register No. 11 includes prisoners admitted from 15 April 1916 to 8 June 1922 (inmate number 14034 to 18162). The register includes date received, name of prisoner, race, where sentenced, crime, term, birthplace (city or county and state), age, term expired, days lost, discharged, location and remarks. A separate volume indexes this register. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [Register, Misc. Reel 5993, frame 0258-0637; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0364-0450]
        Prisoner Register No. 12 includes prisoners admitted from 8 June 1922 to 5 October 1926 (inmate number 18163 to 21585). The register includes date received, name of prisoner, race, where sentenced, crime, term, birthplace (city or county and state), age, term expires, jail time, discharged, location and remarks. Index volume is not extant. [Register, Misc. Reel 5994, frame 0001-0394]
        Prisoner Register No. 13 includes prisoners admitted from 5 October 1926 to 25 October 1929 (inmate number 21586 to 24809). The register includes date received, name of prisoner, race, where sentenced, crime, term, birthplace (city or county and state), age, term expires, jail time, discharged, location and remarks. A separate volume indexes this register. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [Register, Misc. Reel 5994, frame 0395-0754; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0002-0057]
        Prisoner Register No. 14 covering the admission dates between 25 October 1929 and 15 December 1931 (inmate number 24810 to 27773) is not extant. However, the unnumbered Prisoner Registers in this subseries contain similar information on inmates for this time period. A separate index volume for Prisoner Register No. 14 is extant and can be used to access the unnumbered registers.. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [unnumbered Register, inmate number 24810-25834, Misc. Reel 5995, frame 0587-0630 and unnumbered Register, inmate number 25835-27773, Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0002-0081; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0058-0111]
        Prisoner Register No. 15 includes prisoners admitted from 16 December 1931 to 4 October 1933 (inmate number 27774 to 31041). The register includes date received, name of prisoner, race, where sentenced, crime, term, birthplace (city or county and state), age, term expires, jail time, discharged, location and remarks. A separate volume indexes this register. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [Register, Misc. 5995, frame 0002-0352; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0112-0165]
        Prisoner Register No. 16 covering admission dates between 4 October 1933 to 5 July 1935 (inmate number 31042 to 34190) is not extant. However, the unnumbered Prisoner Registers in this subseries contain similar information on inmates for this time period. A separate index volume for Prisoner Register No. 16 is extant and can be used to access the unnumbered registers. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [unnumbered Register, inmate number 31042-34190, Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0218-0352; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0166-0220]
        Prisoner Register No. 17 covering admission dates between 5 July 1935 and 25 March 1937 (inmate number 34191 to 37360) is not extant. However, the unnumbered Prisoner Registers in this subseries contain similar information on inmates for this time period. A separate index volume for Prisoner Register No. 17 is extant and can be used to access the unnumbered registers. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [unnumbered Register, inmate number 34191-37360, Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0352-0475; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0221-0273]
        Prisoner Register No. 18 covering admission dates between 25 March 1937 and 16 November 1938 (inmate number 37361 to 40550) is not extant. However, the unnumbered Prisoner Registers in this subseries contain similar information on inmates for this time period. A separate index volume for Prisoner Register No. 18 is extant and can be used to access the unnumbered registers. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [unnumbered Register, inmate number 37361-40550, Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0475-0571; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0274-0327]
        Prisoner Register No. 19 covering admission dates between 16 November 1938 and 24 October 1940 (inmate number 40551 to 44038) is not extant. However, the unnumbered Prisoner Registers in this subseries contain similar information on inmates for this time period. A separate index volume for Prisoner Register No. 19 is extant and can be used to access the unnumbered registers. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [unnumbered Register, inmate number 40551-40653, Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0571-0573 and unnumbered Register, inmate number 40654-44038, Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0002-0092; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0328-0383]
        Prisoner Register No. 20 covering admission dates between 24 October 1940 and 15 December 1942 (inmate number 44039-47523) is not extant. However, the unnumbered Prisoner Registers in this subseries contain similar information on inmates for this time period. A separate index volume for Prisoner Register No. 20 is extant and can be used to access the unnumbered registers. Index contains name, race and prisoner number. [unnumbered Register, inmate number 44039-47523, Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0092-0171; Index volume, Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0384-0437]
        - Prisoner Register No. 1, 12 June 1865 to 19 January 1869 with a list of convicts admitted to Penitentiary prior to 12 June 1865 (partially indexed beginning with M surnames). (Volume 1, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5989, frame 0001-0242)
        - Prisoner Register No. 2, 19 January 1865 to 24 March 1870 with a list of convicts in penitentiary brought forward from previous register (no index). (Volume 2, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5989, frame 0243-0326)
        - Prisoner Register No. 3, 25 March 1870 to 26 September 1872 with a list of convicts in penitentiary brought forward from previous register (internal index). (Volume 3, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5989, frame 0327-end of reel)
        - Prisoner Register No. 4 (part one), 27 September 1872 to 16 March 1876 (internal index). (Volume 4, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5990, frame 0001-0102)
        - Prisoner Register Book No. 4 (part two), list of convicts in penitentiary brought forward from previous registers (1868-1870) and list of convicts hired out, 1871-1876. (Volume 5, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5990, frame 0103-0241)
        - Prisoner Register No. 5, 17 March 1876 to 30 December 1884 with a list of convicts in penitentiary brought forward from previous registers. (Volume 6, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5990, frame 0242-0605)
        - Prisoner Register No. 6, 5 January 1885 to 29 September 1894. (Volume 7, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5991, frame 0001-0321)
        - Prisoner Register No. 7, 1 October 1894 to 27 September 1902 (Inmate 617 to 4508). (Volume 8, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5991, frame 0322-0713)
        - Prisoner Register No. 8, 28 September 1902 to 30 September 1908 (Inmate 4509 to 8140). (Volume 9, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5992, frame 0001-0016, 0040-0294)
        - Prisoner Register No. 9, 1 October 1908 to 4 November 1912 (Inmate 8141 to 11082). (Volume 10, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5992, frame 0297-0548)
        - Prisoner Register No. 10, 4 November 1912 to 15 April 1916 (Inmate 11083 to 14033). (Volume 11, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5993, frame 0001-0257)
        - Prisoner Register No. 11, 15 April 1916 to 8 June 1922 (Inmate 14034 to 18162). (Volume 12, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5993, frame 0258-0637)
        - Prisoner Register No. 12, 8 June 1922 to 5 October 1926 (Inmate 18163 to 21585). (Volume 13, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5994, frame 0001-0394)
        - Prisoner Register No. 13, 5 October 1926 to 18 October 1929 (Inmate 21586 to 24809). (Volume 14, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5994, frame 0395-0754)
        - Prisoner Register No. 14, 19 October 1929 to 15 December 1931 (Inmate 24810 to 27773)- NOT EXTANT
        - Prisoner Register No. 15, 16 December 1931 to 4 October 1933 (Inmate 27774 to 31041). (Volume 15, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5995, frame 0002-0352)
        - Prisoner Register No. 16, 4 October 1933 to 5 July 1935 (Inmate 31042 to 34190) - NOT EXTANT
        - Prisoner Register No. 17, 5 July 1935 and 25 March 1937 (inmate number 34191 to 37360) - NOT EXTANT
        - Prisoner Register No. 18, 25 March 1937 and 16 November 1938 (inmate number 37361 to 40550) - NOT EXTANT
        - Prisoner Register No. 19, 16 November 1938 and 24 October 1940 (inmate number 40551 to 44038) - NOT EXTANT
        - Prisoner Register No. 20, 24 October 1940 and 15 December 1942 (inmate number 44039-47523) - NOT EXTANT
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 5. (Volume 16, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6002, frame 0335-0402)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 5. (Volume 17, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6002, frame 0403-0432])
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 6. (Volume 18, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6002, frame 0433-0505)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 6. (Volume 19, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6002, frame 0506-0572)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 7. (Volume 20, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0001-0061)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 7. (Volume 21, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0062-0107)
        - Index to Prisoner Registers No. 7 and No. 8. (Volume 22, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0108-0226)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 8. (Volume 23, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0227-0287)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 9. (Volume 24, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0288-0327)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 10. (Volume 25, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0328-0363)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 11. (Volume 26, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6003, frame 0364-0450)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 12 - NOT EXTANT
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 13. (Volume 27, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0002-0057)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 14 - REGISTER NOT EXTANT. (Volume 28, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0058-0111)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 15. (Volume 29, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0112-0165)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 16 - REGISTER NOT EXTANT. (Volume 30, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0166-0220)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 17 - REGISTER NOT EXTANT. (Volume 31, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0221-0273)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 18 - REGISTER NOT EXTANT. (Volume 32, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0274-0327)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 19 - REGISTER NOT EXTANT. (Volume 33, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0328-0383)
        - Index to Prisoner Register No. 20 - REGISTER NOT EXTANT. (Volume 34, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6004, frame 0384-0437)
      - II.A.I.2. Unnumbered Prisoner Registers, 1924-1945. (Volumes 35-39.)
        There are five volumes of unnumbered Prisoner Registers for prisoners admitted between 3 January 1924 and 20 February 1945. While these volumes overlap with the numbered registers, they also fill in the gaps within the collection. Unlike the numbered registers, these do not include information on the age and birthplace of prisoner. The reason and purpose for these duplicate registers is unknown. The unnumbered volumes are not indexed. However, researchers should use the extant index volumes described in Subseries A.I.1. Prisoner Registers and Indexes to obtain the prisoner number to check these volumes.
        The first unnumbered Prisoner Register includes prisoners admitted from 3 January 1924 to 7 August 1930 (inmate number 19253 to 25834). The register includes name of prisoner, sentence, date received, date discharged, crime, where sentenced, race and assignment (penitentiary, state farm, road camp, etc.). [Misc. Reel 5995, frame 0356-0630]
        The second unnumbered Prisoner Register includes prisoners admitted from 7 August 1930 to 4 March 1935 (inmate number 25835 to 33561). The register includes name of prisoner, sentence, date received, date discharged, crime, where sentenced, race and assignment (penitentiary, state farm, road camp, etc.). [Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0001-0322]
        The third unnumbered Prisoner Register includes prisoners admitted from 5 March 1935 to 9 December 1938 (inmate number 33562 to 40653). The register includes name of prisoner, sentence, date received, date discharged, crime, where sentenced, race and assignment (penitentiary, state farm, road camp, etc.). [Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0323-0573]
        The fourth unnumbered Prisoner Register includes prisoners admitted from 9 December 1938 to 11 December 1942 (inmate number 40654 to 47513). The register includes name of prisoner, sentence, date received, date discharged, crime, where sentenced, race and assignment (penitentiary, state farm, road camp, etc.). [Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0001-0169]
        The fifth unnumbered Prisoner Register includes prisoners admitted from 15 December 1942 to 20 February 1945 (inmate numbers 47514 to 50271). The register includes name of prisoner, sentence, date received, date discharged, crime, where sentenced, race and assignment (penitentiary, state farm, road camp, etc.). In addition, this register indicates if the prisoner has been evaluated by a psychiatrist, dentist and physician. This volume does not contain any medical information. [Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0170-0234]
        - Prisoner Register [no number], 3 January 1924 to 7 August 1930 (Inmate 19253 to 25834). (Volume 35, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5995, frame 0356-0630)
        - Prisoner Register [no number], 7 August 1930 to 4 March 1935 (Inmate 25835 to 33561) (Volume 36, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0001-0322)
        - Prisoner Register [no number], 5 March 1935 to 9 December 1938 (Inmate 33562 to 40653). (Volume 37, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5996, frame 0323-0573)
        - Prisoner Register [no number], 9 December 1938 to 11 December 1942 (Inmate 40654 to 47513). (Volume 38, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0001-0169)
        - Prisoner Register [no number], 15 December 1942 to 20 February 1945 (Inmate 47514 to 50271) (Volume 39, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0170-0234)
      - II.A.I.3. Prison Books, 1922-1980. (Volumes 40-49.)
        At some point during the 1940s, the numbering system for the registers started over and the information in the first three "new" volumes overlapped with information found in the numbered and unnumbered Prisoner Registers. The new volumes are not indexed and the volumes are incomplete. However, researchers should use the extant index volumes to check these new volumes.
        Prison Book No. 1 was created sometime in the early 1940s and includes prisoners admitted from 1922 to 1933 (inmate number 15356 to 29995). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Most of the entries in this volume are blank. See the numbered and unnumbered Prisoner Registers for complete information on inmates admitted from 1924 to 1933. [Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0237-0613]
        Prison Book No. 2 was created sometime in the early 1940s and includes prisoners admitted from 20 March 1933 to 21 July 1938 (inmate number 29996 to 39995). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Most of the entries in this volume are blank. See the numbered and unnumbered Prisoner Registers for complete information on inmates admitted from 1933 to 1938. [Misc. Reel 5998, frame 0001-0252]
        Prison Book No. 3 includes prisoners admitted from 21 July 1938 to 3 December 1944 (inmate number 39996 to 49999). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. See the unnumbered Prisoner Registers for complete information on inmates admitted from 1938 to 1944. [Misc. Reel 5998, frame 0253-0514]
        Prison Book No. 4 includes prisoners admitted from 3 December 1944 to 15 February 1951 (inmate number 50000 to 59999). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 5999, frame 0001-0262]
        Prison Book No. 5 includes prisoners admitted from 8 March 1951 to 4 September 1956 (inmate number 60000 to 70035). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 5999, frame 0263-0528]
        Prison Book No. 6 includes prisoners admitted from 4 September 1956 to 20 July 1961 (inmate numbers 70036 to 80032). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 6000, frame 0001-0253]
        Prison Book No. 7 includes prisoners admitted from 20 July 1961 to 28 August 1967 (inmate numbers 80033 to 89999). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 6000, frame 0254-0509]
        Prison Book No. 8 includes prisoners admitted from 29 August 1967 to 24 October 1972 (inmate number 90000 to 99999). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 6001, frame 0001-0256]
        Prison Book No. 9 includes prisoners admitted from 24 October 1972 to 29 April 1976 (inmate number 100000 to 107999). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, jail time, sentence, date received, date released, charge, place of conviction, sent to, out date, returned date, discharged or pardoned and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 6001, frame 0257-0459]
        Prison Book No. 10 includes prisoners admitted from 29 April 1976 to 10 July 1980 (inmate number 108000 to 121189). The book includes number, name of prisoner, race, date of birth, date received, warrant number, previous number, place of conviction and remarks. Volume is not indexed. [Misc. Reel 6002, frame 0001-0332]
        - Prison Book No. 1, 1922 to 1933 (Inmate 15356 to 29995). (Volume 40, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5997, frame 0237-0613)
        - Prison Book No. 2, 11 March 1933 to 21 July 1938 (Inmate 29996 to 39995). (Volume 41, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5998, frame 0001-0252)
        - Prison Book No. 3, 21 July 1938 to 3 December 1944 (Inmate 39996 to 49999). (Volume 42, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5998, frame 0253-0514)
        - Prison Book No. 4, 3 December 1944 to 15 February 1951 (Inmate 50000 to 59999). (Volume 43, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5999, frame 0001-0262)
        - Prison Book No. 5, 8 March 1951 to 4 September 1956 (Inmate 60000 to 70035). (Volume 44, Microfilm Misc. Reel 5999, frame 0263-0528)
        - Prison Book No. 6, 4 September 1956 to 20 July 1961 (Inmate 70036 to 80032). (Volume 45, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6000, frame 0001-0253)
        - Prison Book No. 7, 20 July 1961 to 28 August 1967 (Inmate 80033 to 89999). (Volume 46, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6000, frame 0254-0509)
        - Prison Book No. 8, 29 August 1967 to 24 October 1972 (Inmate 90000 to 99999). (Volume 47, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6001, frame 0001-0256)
        - Prison Book No. 9, 24 October 1972 to 29 April 1976 (Inmate 100000 to 107999). (Volume 48, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6001, frame 0257-0459)
        - Prison Book No. 10, 29 April 1976 to 10 July 1980 (Inmate 108000 to 121189) (Volume 49, Microfilm Misc. Reel 6002, frame 0001-0332)
    - Series II. Subseries A. Registers, A.II. Records of Convicts Received, 1880-1953. (Volumes 50-78 and 270.)
      There are 30 volumes of Records of Convicts Received, from 1880 to1953 and are further divided into A.II.1. Education, Moral and Social Conditions, 1880-1904; A.II.2. Prisoner Receipt Books, 1895-1899, 1901-1912, 1910-1915, 1932-1942; A.II.3. Classification Log Books, undated; A.II.4. Ledger of Inmates, ca. 1920 to 1953; and A.II.5. Prisoner Registers - Rough Drafts, 1912-1925, 1930-1943. The Index to Prisoner Register may serve as an index to most of these records.
      - II.A.II.1. Education, Moral and Social Conditions, 1880-1904. (Volumes 50.)
        The Education, Moral and Social Conditions of Convicts volume lists the convicts received by fiscal year between 1880 and 1904. Included are the name of prisoner, race, social relations (married or single), educational relations (read, write, illiterate), moral condition (intemperate, moderate drinker or temperate) and occupation.
        - Record of Convicts Received during the Fiscal Year, 1880-1881 to 1903-1904. (Volume 50)
      - II.A.II.2. Prisoner Receipt Books, 1895-1899, 1901-1912, 1910-1915 and 1932-1942. (Volumes 51-59.)
        The Prisoner Receipt Books (9 volumes - 1895 to 1899, 1901 to 1912, 1910 to 1915 and 1932 to 1942 are arranged chronologically and by inmate number. Each volume lists the prisoner name, date received, race, where sentenced, crime, term and name of guard paid to transport prisoner to the penitentiary.
        - 1 July 1895 to 19 April 1899. (Volume 51)
        - October 1901 to December 1907. (Volume 52)
        - January 1908 to December 1912. (Volume 53)
        - 1 January 1910 to 31 July 1915. (Volume 54)
        - 12 October 1922 to 14 July 1928. (Volume 55)
        - 1 March 1932 to 15 October 1934. (Volume 56)
        - 16 October 1934 to 28 April 1937. (Volume 57)
        - 29 April 1937 to 5 November 1939. (Volume 58)
        - 8 November 1939 to 10 September 1942. (Volume 59)
      - II.A.II.3. Classfication Log Books, undated. (Volumes 60-68, 270.)
        The Classification Log Books (10 volumes) are arranged by inmate number. Each volume includes name, inmate number, race and assignment within the correctional system (penitentiary, state farm, road camp, etc.). Two volumes also include the date the inmate was received. These volumes are handwritten and several overlap.
        - Inmate 27800 to 34247. (Volume 60)
        - Inmate 46600 to 54499. (Volume 61)
        - Inmate 54500 to 62699. (Volume 62)
        - Inmate 46600 to 55499. (Volume 63)